Johnathan J. Flaggs

LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/johnathanflaggs
Email: work.johnathanflaggs@gmail.com
Website: resume.johnathanflaggs.com

Phone: +1.949.414.9545

Robotics Software Engineer & Architect with a focus on backend system development for robotics applications. Experienced within numerous industries, languages, and technologies. Strong aptitude for mechanical design and has a successful record of leading projects from proof of concept into production.

Education

University of California, Riverside & Davis

Sep. 2010-Jun. 2014

- UCR: BSME with concentration in Control Theory under Department of Mechanical Engineering (BCOE)
- UCD: Control Theory Concentration under Department of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering

Technical Toolset

Development Languages & Environments:

■ Visual Studio	Codeblocks	SVN, GIT, Jira	Ignition SCADA	Node.js
- Visual Studio	- COUCDIOCKS	- 5 v i v, Gi i , Jii a	- Igilition SCADA	- Nouc.js

Atmel Studio
 Embedded C, C++
 C# .NET
 MATLAB, Python
 HTML, CSS, JS

RSLogix/FactoryTalk
 Beckhoff/TwinCAT
 Festo, MagneMotion
 Fanuc TP, Karel
 Cognex, iRVision

RS-232/485, CANbus • Allen Bradley • IEC 61131-3 • gRPC, JSON, SQL • EtherCAT, EtherNet/IP

Professional Experience

Lead Robotics Software Engineer at CarbonCapture

Jun. 2023-Present

Driving system software architecture and automation development for modular Direct Air Capture (DAC) reactors. Ensuring that our team builds a software core that is sufficiently robust, scalable, and maintainable to support current and future product deployments. Leading hiring efforts, defining technical infrastructure, and building company culture to support a quickly growing technical team.

- Identify development resource needs and coordinate efforts with HR and VP to create new technical positions
- Manage sprint cycles and review source code on a per-commit basis to avoid common development pitfalls
- Hosted a bi-weekly coding program wherein Jr. and Sr. developers can learn and share their contributions
- Establish clear and achievable performance expectations and conduct regular performance evaluations
- Synchronize a team of mechanical, software, process, and data science engineers on a weekly basis
- Interface with contractors for outsourcing code and supplying measurement/control devices
- Mentor engineers on approaching complex problems and upkeeping best coding standards
- Drive design of macro and micro software architectures which define the core product
- Anticipate and mitigate the impact of future design changes on the software layers
- Enforced OOP and heavy emphasis on robustness, scalability, maintainability, and patterns in C#/C++, and TwinCAT
 - o Increased software scalability/maintainability by refactoring code from FP to OOP
- Drive strategic decisions regarding budget, mechanical design, safety, maintenance, and scalability
 - o Reduced materials budget by over \$100k by eliminating need for absolute encoders
 - o Eliminated expensive door motors by proposing pneumatic actuation design

Professional Experience

Lead Controls Engineer at Essentium 3D

Jun. 2021-Jun. 2023

Leading robotics software architecture and development for high-speed industrial 3D printers. Ensuring that our team builds a software core that is sufficiently robust, scalable, and maintainable to support the product line. I refactored the existing code base into OOP scalable modules/layers. This allowed us to quickly change hardware and ultimately extend from plastics into metal printing.

- Lead the design and architecture of our core software which allowed us to expand from plastic to metal printing
- Primarily used Clearcore Teknic controllers for real-time control and C# for the application and UI layers
- Mentor Jr. Engineers on approaching complex problems and upkeeping best coding standards
- OOP and heavy emphasis on robustness, scalability, maintainability, and patterns in C# and C++
- Anticipate and mitigate the impact of future design changes on the software layers
- **Design** of macro and micro software architectures which define the core product
- Manage and review source control on a per-commit basis

Sr. Robotics Software Engineer at Seagate Technology

Mar. 2017-Jun. 2021

Developing software for cutting edge processes in digital storage technology. I focused on developing complex motion control routines for pico-scale positioning, calibration routines, state-machine process synchronization, and machine vision integration using the Congnex SDK.

- Primarily used Beckhoff and Delta Tau for real-time control and C#/C++ for vision, application, and UI layers
- Motion Control Kinematics, pick-n-place, multi-axis coordination, Quantum HSM framework
- OOP Heavy emphasis on encapsulation, inheritance, polymorphism, and robust design patterns
- User Interface Allowing users to fluidly interact with the multi-threaded application
- User Interface Allowing users to fluidly interact with the multi-threaded application
- Machine-Vision Calibration to establish precision robot coordinate system
- Version Control Using SVN, TFS and Agile/Scrum using Jira
- Support core vision libraries in C/C++
- Cognex VisionPro API integration

Lead Controls Engineer at Sorenson Engineering Inc.

Sep. 2014-Mar. 2017

Leading controls software development for high-volume manufacturing. I developed core software and worked closely with Mechanical Engineers to build proof of concept products (R&D environment).

- Primarily used Beckhoff, Festo, Maxxon, and Jenny Science for real-time control with TwinCAT for HMI/UI
- Motion Control Kinematics, motor sizing, pick-n-place, multi-axis synchronization, and axis coupling
- Increased machine PPM by decreasing rotor inertia ratio by 140% for tighter position control (VSIII)
- Fieldbus Integration Integrating multiple OEM device nodes into the EtherCAT controls network
- Vision Inspection Driving digital cameras (Cognex, Baumer/VeriSens) via native C++ SDKs
- Eliminated need for expensive camming software license and a measurement sensor